这个视频是关于脚本的，
脚本就像是在比特币中用来锁定你的比特币的迷你编程语言。
当你要给别人发送比特币时，
你实际上在这些比特币上面加了一个小型的编程语言来锁定它们。
然后当他们要解锁它们时，
他们需要提供一些更多的代码，
当它与原始的锁定代码一起运行时，
它将开始工作，这些比特币就可以被花费了。
这就是脚本。
让我们从上次的演示中继续，
假设这是一批比特币，
世界上存在的每一批比特币都有一个锁。
当你想要进行交易时，
你会解锁那批比特币，
从中创建一批新的比特币，
并在上面放一个新的锁，
这就是一个简单的交易，
就是取出一批比特币，
解锁它们，创建新的批次并锁定它们。
当你要进行新的交易时，
你就再次做同样的事情，
你只是解锁一个现有的批次，
创建一个新的批次，
并在上面放一个新的锁，
这就是比特币交易系统的工作原理。
这是一个简化的一系列交易，
如果你想了解更多关于交易如何进行的信息，
请观看我之前做的关于交易的视频。
但这只涵盖了比特币批次的基本移动。
所以这意味着，当你想要给别人发送比特币时，
你需要取出一批你可以解锁的比特币。
比如说这是你，这是一批只有你可以解锁的比特币
我过一会儿会解释这是如何工作的，
但现在请相信我，
你是唯一可以解锁这批比特币的人。
这就是你要做的，
你想要给某人发送一些比特币。
这个方法的工作原理是，
你会创建一批带有锁的比特币。
只有这个人可以解锁，
这是因为在比特币中，
每个人都有自己的私钥和公钥，
这就像每个人都有自己的密码和账号一样。
当你想要给某人发送比特币时，
他们会给你他们的公钥，
你将创建一个交易，
并锁定一些你拥有的比特币，
创建一批新的比特币，
然后在这批比特币的锁上放置他们的公钥。
这就是为什么这个人拥有这批比特币的原因，
因为这批比特币的锁上包含了他们的公钥，
这是他们的唯一账号。
如果他们想要花费这批比特币或者发送给其他人，
他们将使用他们的私钥，
就像他们的账号的密码一样，来解锁它。
他们会从私钥创建一个签名，
这就像一个一次性密码。
任何人看到这个签名和这个公钥，
都能够确定这个签名只能由拥有这个公钥的私钥的人创建。
没有人能够创建一个能够与这个公钥特定匹配的签名。
我在密钥和地址的视频中介绍了如何进行这个操作，
但在这个视频，我只会介绍锁定机制，
如果你对这些签名、私钥、公钥的来源以及工作原理感兴趣，
可以观看那个视频。
在常规交易中，
比特币被锁定到一个公钥，
然后当你想要解锁它们时，
你提供一个签名来解锁它们，
以证明你是这个公钥的所有者，
因为你拥有从这个公钥创建的私钥。
任何人都可以查看签名，
与公钥进行对比，看到它们匹配，
如果它们匹配，
然后这些比特币可以被解锁并在新的交易中使用，
它们可以被发送给其他人。
显然，这批比特币将包含别人的公钥，
这就是使用这些公钥和签名进行交易的方式。
所以在这个视频中，就像我说的，
我不会涉及交易和这些密钥是如何工作的。
我只会关注锁定代码和解锁代码是如何交互的。
这里有一个锁定机制，我们会在基础知识中介绍，
你会发现这只是一个小型的编程语言坐在这些锁里，
同样的事情再次出现在解锁代码里。
实际上有很多不同的，
因为这是一个位于这些锁内的编程语言，
你可以创建不同类型的锁。
我会介绍每种最常见的锁的工作原理，
这是P2PK，
这是最常见、最简单的锁定比特币的方式，
对于锁定比特币很重要，
还有P2PKH，
这非常相似，但稍微复杂一些，
这是现在最常见的比特币锁定。
然后是P2MS，和P2SH，
这些是你可以放在比特币批次上的最常见类型的锁。
最后我会用一些代码和例子来结束，
向你展示实际的脚本运行，
向你展示它是多么简单。
但在这个演示结束时，
希望你你会熟悉所有这些不同的术语，
如果你在研究比特币，
你可能已经碰到了其中一些术语。
但最终，如果你理解了基础的脚本是一种迷你编程语言，
所以，到目前为止有任何问题吗？
首先是基础知识，
这两部分的锁是如何互动的呢？
到现在为止，
我一直使用这个小锁符号来说明放在比特币批次上的锁。
这只是一些包含一个叫做脚本的迷你编程语言的代码。
我们称这个锁住一批比特币的代码为锁定脚本。
这个锁定脚本被放在这个第一笔交易的输出上，
当这些比特币被创建或者输出被创建的时候。
然后在你想要解锁这批比特币并从中创建新的批次时，
你需要提供一些额外的代码来匹配这个锁定脚本，
这就叫做解锁脚本。
这个锁定部分通常被称为脚本公钥，
因为它通常包含一个公钥，
并且显然是一个脚本。
这个解锁脚本有时被称为脚本签名，
因为它也是一个脚本，
并且通常包含一个签名。
但是在这个视频中，
我会坚持称它们锁定脚本和解锁脚本，
因为我认为它们更具描述性，
而且并不是所有的脚本公钥都需要包含一个公钥，
也不是所有的解锁脚本都需要包含一个签名。
我更喜欢更通用和多功能的使用锁定脚本和解锁脚本这两个术语。
这就是这些脚本的基础知识。
那么它是如何交互的呢？
我们在这个小型编程语言中可以使用的是这些叫做操作码的东西，
它们就像是内置在脚本语言中的小型函数。
对于特定类型的锁定有好处，
我们称它为CHECKSIG。
我们将其放入锁定脚本中。
现在我们有了一个完整的脚本，
包括锁定部分和解锁部分。
这个特定的函数将会检查一个签名与公钥是否匹配。
你可能猜到了这种脚本将如何运行和验证。
就像我说的，每个脚本只包含一些数据，
比如这里的公钥和签名，
以及一些操作符或操作码，
这就是脚本的全部内容，
只有一些数据和一些被称为操作码的函数。
当你试图将这个交易插入到比特币网络，
或者说任何一个节点中时，
他们会接收这个完整的脚本。
他们会接收最初放在输出上的锁定脚本，
然后他们会接收你提供的解锁脚本并运行整个脚本以确保它验证通过。
如果验证通过，
那么这个交易就是有效的，
可以添加到区块链中，或者说他们会接受它，
并将其转发给其他节点
甚至是矿工，
他们有可能将其挖掘到区块链上。
如果你创建了一个更复杂的交易，
你选择了许多不同的输出作为这个交易的输入，
每一个都会有自己的锁定脚本，
所以你需要为每一个提供解锁脚本，
每一个解锁脚本也必须对整个交易有效，
整个交易才能被网络上的节点接受。
这就是脚本的基础，
它只是一些数据和一些函数。
这是如何运行的呢？
就像我说的那样，
你可能会猜到它是如何运行，
我将介绍节点如何运行整个脚本的步骤。
我有个小问题，
解锁脚本是交易的一部分，
而我们所说的锁定脚本，
实际上就是数字签名。
你提到的解锁脚本，
实际上是由花费比特币的人创建的。
谢谢你的回答，
在第一个交易中，
某人会设置这个锁定代码。
这个人就会进行这笔交易，
并将解锁代码放在这里
当他来解锁它时，
他们只需要引用这批比特币，
并将解锁代码输入到这个交易中。
整个脚本实际上是分布在两个不同的交易中。
这个新的锁定脚本会被放在这个交易的顶部。
这有点复杂，
因为锁定部分和解锁部分实际上是在两个不同的交易中。
所以如果你看这一笔交易，
实际上不会有一整个脚本来一起运行，
它可能稍后在运行，
据我所知，解锁脚本，
就是那个红色的波浪，
它将是黄色交易的一部分，
在这个特定的交易中
在交易数据中有输入和输出，
对于每个输入，
我们实际上并没有看到或输入这个锁定代码，
我们所做的就是为我们选择的每个输入应用或输入一个锁定代码。
即使我已经把锁定代码放在这里，
实际上不会看到它们。
然后在交易的第二部分，我们创建输出时，
我们将在这里放一些新的锁定代码，
无论我们想要什么样的锁。
输入有解锁代码，
输出有锁定代码。
我想当我在最后展示交易数据时，
你可能会更能理解。
这有点令人困惑，
因为我把这个锁定代码放在这里，
但在这个交易中，
你实际上不会看到锁定代码，
我们只知道它在那里，
所以我们只是在这里引用它，
我现在继续运行这个完整脚本的内容。
当一个节点接收到一个交易时，
他们会有解锁代码，
并且他们有对之前有锁定代码的输出的引用，
它们将获取整个内容并一起运行，
节点如何运行这两部分脚本来确保这批比特币可以被解锁和花费呢?
他们会把这个解锁代码，
它是在这个二级交易中提供的，
将其放在锁定代码的前面，
像这样，
然后他们将从左到右运行这个脚本。
他们运行这个代码的方式是使用一个叫做栈的数据结构，
如果你之前做过任何编程，
栈就是一个简单的数据结构，
它很像一个数组，
我们只是在栈顶或数组的末尾推入和弹出元素
我们有这个脚本，一堆数据和函数，
它们都在栈顶上运行。
所以我们现在会用这个栈从左到右运行这个脚本。
首先，当我们从左到右进行时，
我们遇到了一些数据，签名，
你在脚本中遇到的任何数据都会被推入栈顶，
所以这个签名再次被推入了栈顶。
我们遇到了一个公钥，
这只是更多的数据，
它也会被推入栈顶。
最后，我们遇到了一个操作码，
操作码与数据的操作方式有些不同。
数据只是被推入栈顶，
而操作码可以做什么呢？
它会从栈顶弹出一个或多个项目，
对它们执行某些操作后，
它可以选择性地在堆栈顶部推回项目，
在处理这些项目之后，
我们会使用CHECKSIG，
它会从堆栈顶部弹出两个项目。
这里，它弹出了公钥和签名，
然后它会对这两个项目做一些处理。
CHECKSIG会检查这个签名是否匹配这个公钥，
或者这个签名是否是这个特定公钥的有效签名。
如果你想了解这个过程，你就可以去看看关于密钥和地址的视频。
你就可以去看看关于密钥和地址的视频。
但是这个例子，
让我们假设这个签名是这个公钥的有效签名。
在CHECKSIG操作完成后
如果这个签名是有效的，
它会把1推到堆栈的顶部。
或将数字1推到堆栈的顶部。
这个脚本就被完全执行了。
那么什么使这个脚本是有效的呢，
或者说一批比特币可以被花费吗？
如果在运行整个脚本后，
堆栈顶部留下了一个1，
那么这就意味着这个脚本是有效的，
这批比特币可以被花费。
如果在脚本运行后，
堆栈为空，则它无效，
如果在整个脚本运行后堆栈顶部留下零，
那么脚本同样无效。
因此在这最后一个示例中，
如果这个检查签名没有正确执行，
我认为它会将零或者什么都不推到堆栈顶部，
可能是零，堆栈就会被判定为无效。
但在这个示例中，
签名与公钥匹配，
检查签名操作码执行所有这些操作，
如果正确，
它会将1推到堆栈顶部，
如果在脚本运行后堆栈顶部留下1，
那么这批比特币可以被花费，这是有道理的。
让我把这些都移回来，
我们知道为什么刚才有一个所谓的p2pk的例子，
它非常简单，
一批比特币上的锁定代码只包含别人的公钥和检查签名操作码，
然后当那个人想要解锁他们时，
他们要的就是解锁这批比特币
我所要做的是提供私钥的有效签名，
该公钥是从现在开始创建的，
这可能是锁定一批比特币的最简单的方式，
矿工们在区块内的coinbase交易中大量使用了这种方式，
但通常今天我们使用这种锁定机制的一种变体。
这是最简单的一种，
但我们现在使用的是一种有点不同的东西。
这被称为Pay To Pubkey或简称P2PK。
请注意，这些P 2 P K和Pay To Pubkey，
这些名字适用于你应用到一批比特币的锁定脚本的模式。
所以如果你看到一批比特币，
它有一个公钥和一个检查操作码，没有别的，
那个模式就是一个Pay To Pubkey脚本，
这个脚本是一组最常用的标准脚本中的一个。
我将介绍其中的五个，
这是最简单的一个，
叫做Pay To Pubkey。
接下来我们有一个叫做Pay To Pubkey Hash的，
它与这个非常相似，只是稍微有些不同，
我会在一会儿后解释原因。
如果你还记得在关于密钥和地址的视频中，
我们创建了一个私钥和公钥，
这就是我们在比特币中发送和接收比特币所需要的全部，
我们通常会先对公钥进行哈希，
我提到这是因为安全性，
我认为，这主要是因为一开始，
这是一种简单的减小公钥大小的方式，
所以当我们把这个给别人的时候。
of the public key so that's when we give
我们可以给他们一个更小的公钥，
但这仍然是我们的公钥，
but it's still a unique vision of our
所以我们会做的是，
public key so what we would do
当我们创建了我们的密钥和地址后，
whence we've created our keys in the
我们会对我们的公钥进行哈希，
dress is we will hash our public key
这样就减小了它的大小，
which produces its size we'll give that
然后我们会将这个哈希值给别人，
some else and then they'll put that into
然后他们会将这个哈希值放入锁定代码中，
the locking code instead of our original
而不是我们原来的公钥，
public key so the way this particular
这种特殊的锁定脚本是使用我们公钥的哈希版本，
而不是标准的原始公钥。
standard you know original public key is
我们会在它周围放一个类似的锁定脚本，
we put a locking script like this around
it so it's a little bit similar we still
我们仍然有这个检查签名函数，
have this check sync function but now
但现在不是只有哈希公钥和check sig，
instead of having the public key and
just the check sig we have hash the
我们对哈希公钥和这些额外的操作码进行哈希处理。
public key and these extra operators
稍后就会知道原因。
here and we'll see why in a moment so
这就是Pay To Pubkey Hash，
this is the paid up key hash pattern or
或者说Pay To Pubkey Hash锁定脚本，
the pattern for a paid-up key hash
当你来解锁这个特定的锁定脚本时
我们需要做的就像之前一样，
what we need to do like before all we
我们需要一个签名，
need is a signature from for from the
这个签名来自于生成这个公钥的私钥，
private key that this public key is made
除此之外，
from and then also in addition to that
我们还需要提供原始的公钥。
we all need to provide the original
当一个节点来运行这个脚本，
确保它是有效的时，
to make sure it's valid they do the same
他们会再次确保解锁脚本从左到右运行。
他们会把他们的堆栈，
left to right so what they'll do they'll
显然数据会被推到堆栈上，
take their stack they'll obviously data
签名会在顶部，
gets pushed onto the stack the signature
然后是公钥。
goes on top top then the public key let
然后我们遇到这个复制操作码，
me hit this dupe up code and it does
它会做你期望它做的事情，
what you expect it would it pops the top
它会弹出堆栈的顶部元素，复制它，
element of the stack duplicates it and
然后把这个复制的顶部元素推回到堆栈上。
我们有哈希160，
done next up we have the hash 160
它会弹出顶部元素，对它进行哈希，
that'll pop the top element off hash it
然后把它推回到堆栈的顶部。
and then push it back on top of the
然后我们来看原始锁定脚本中的哈希公钥，
start then we went into the hashed
public key that was a in the original
它被推到了顶部。
locking script that gets pushed on top
然后我们来到EQUALVERIFY操作码，
then we went into the equal verify
这个操作码会从堆栈的顶部弹出两个元素，
检查它们是否相等，如果它们相等，
checks are they equal and if they are
它不会把任何东西推回到堆栈上。
equal it won't push anything back onto
然后是EQUALVERIFY操作码，
the stack so whereas the equal up code
它会把1推到堆栈的顶部，
would push the number one on top equal
检查签名是否匹配公钥，
verify checks the equal and if they are
如果匹配，它不会把任何内容推回到堆栈上。
doesn't push anything on top of the
然后我们遇到了熟悉的CHECKSIG操作码，
该代码将弹出，
pop to its off check that the signature
检查签名与公钥是否匹配，
matches the public key and if it does
如果匹配，它会把一个数字推到堆栈的顶部。
you're pushing one on to the top of the
所以与pay to pub key hash的唯一真正区别是，
你需要检查你提供的公钥，
是否与最初提供的公钥的哈希匹配，
如果匹配，
it does it will just check the signature
它就会像Pay To Pubkey 那样检查签名。
有其他问题吗？
我们是否可以自己创建，
are you aware if we can come up with our
比如Pay To Pubkey，
own like you know you have paid to
比如Pay To Pubkey Hash，
publicly paid to public key hash let's
假设我想做一个Pay To Pubkey Hash，
say I want to do a play to public key
这是用户实际可以做的吗？
hash of hash is that something that
答案是肯定的，
users can actually do yes yes yes yes I
我会在稍后解释为什么。
know and I'll explain why in a moment
好的问题，
but good question okay oh yeah I'll come
现在我将继续讲解这些标准脚本。
Pay To Pubkey和Pay To Pubkey Hash相同，
它只是首先检查你在解锁脚本中提供的公钥哈希是否与最初提供的哈希匹配，
然后像往常一样检查签名。
just check the singer's normal so this
我想说，
Pay To Pubkey是针对公钥的，
yeah people pika is for the public keys
而Pay To Pubkey Hash是针对比特币地址的。
but we do PK H is for the Bitcoin
是的，
这是你在比特币上最常见的锁定脚本。
为了方便实用，
days for convenience instead of when you
当你想接收比特币时，
want to receive bitcoins instead of you
我们有一种更方便的方式，而不是创建这个哈希，
know creating this hash and then
然后用你想用的所有操作码包围它，
surrounding it with all the opcodes you
基本上构造了整个锁定脚本，
want to use around it so basically
construct this entire lock-in script and
然后给别人。
then giving it to someone else
我们在比特币中有很多更方便的方法来做到这一点，
我们创建一个地址，
we create an address which is basically
这基本上是公钥的哈希160，
a the hash 160 of the public key
转换成用户更好使用的格式，
converted into a more user-friendly
它有一个校验和，
format it has a checksum and uses more
使用对用户更友好的字符。
user-friendly characters so it's harder
to make make mistakes with and then this
address will be prepended with a one at
the front so that means if you give an
address to someone else where the one at
the start they will be able to decode it
to get the original hash of the public
key and because they see that there's a
one at the front they'll go okay this
person wants to pay to pub key hash so
they will decode it and form this
locking script with the
hache 160 the public key placed inside
it so this address here is just a
convenient way of telling people how you
want your bitcoins to be locked up
so Peter PK does not have a address
format so if you want bitcoins to be
locked up in this format you have to
send them the entire locking script and
the after the person will have to
construct the transaction manually to
put this locking script inside but the
Pater pub key hash the more common
format has this address so whenever you
send someone an address all you're
sending them is the hash of your public
key and telling them to lock it up in a
certain way thirdly I'm gonna do five
just a third one so these are just pay
into a single person's public key you
have what's called pay to multi-sig so
what you can do in Bitcoin instead of
just lock in a batch of bitcoins up to
one person's public key see there are
three of you in a company or inside a
business and you want to receive
bitcoins together or you can do you can
all put your public keys into a locking
script and then what you'll do your put
in number after it which is n the number
of public keys inside the locking script
and then another number called M which
is the number of signatures that needs
to be provided for this locking script
to be unlocked or this but so I
Bitcoin assign to be unlocked and then
at the end of it then you'll use the
check multi-sig function so this is a
Peter multi-sig locking script so like I
said the M here just indicates how many
signatures are going to be needed for
this lock in scope to be unlocked
so when it comes to so say you give this
locking script to someone else they put
a batch of bitcoins with this locking
script on it so when these three people
here want to come to unlock this batch
of bitcoins are send them on to someone
else or we all need is two signatures
from any two of these people they also
need to be in the correct order so if
these public keys were put into the
locking code in a specific order these
signatures will be need to be in the
correct order also which you will see
why in a moment
so that is a typical Paton multi-sig and
I'll run it in a moment just a quick
note there's a little bug in this check
multi-sig function or the way it works
and this was just a boat from the start
of Bitcoin that we just need to account
for now basically what happens is the M
at the start here has an off by one
error so what happens is it will consume
one more item from the stack then we've
indicated here so to get around that for
every pay to multi-sig we just need to
put a dummy or zero opcode at the start
so this is the bug that need to account
for let me use the check multi-sig
script so anyway let's run this script
how does it get run how does it get
checked and put the locking code at the
start then go from left to right numbers
they just get pushed onto the stack
just like data like so so the zeros on
the stack there then we push on the
signatures because their data then we
have the two again number just gets
pushed numbers just get pushed on top of
the stack then each of these public keys
again they're just data can push on top
the stack and then the three finally we
come to the check mark multi-sig opcode
what this does first of all it'll pop
the top element off see that's a three
when it sees us a three it means it will
pop the next three elements off the top
the stack then you'll pop the next
element off which is a two and when it
sees that it'll pop the next 2 ms off
the stack
but like I mentioned earlier this M here
hasn't off by one error so it will
consume three instead of two but this is
just a little bug in Bitcoin attack you
can pretend it's not there anyway so now
it has to come to check the signatures
against the public keys that's why
you'll do it we'll start with the first
signature it's got at the bottom of the
stack and then check it against the
first public key there's got to check
there's and check their matches so let's
say this to it and doesn't match but
that's fine
if that doesn't match it I'll move on to
the next public key to see if that
matches and this one does much so let's
put a little one here to see the lab
matter that hasn't matched the reason I
said to put these signatures into the
correct order is because after the check
multi-sig function has checked a
signature against public keys it won't
check those public keys again so when
you come to match the second signature
against the public keys instead of going
from the start and match them against
each of the individual public keys it
will start from where it left off or the
last match so again you'll check the
signature against this public key here
if that matches the near we are we have
got too much in signatures and therefore
because we asked for asked for - after
three signatures for this lock in script
this script is Viator check multi-sig is
happy with this so it'll push a one on
top of the stack obviously if there's
only 0 or 1 matches signatures for these
public keys they were pushes you on top
but because we've got enough matching
signatures it pushes a one on top of the
stack as that make sense ok so there we
are
8a multi-sig obviously now you know how
these scripts work is quite simple
before we move on to the fourth one
there's a little bit of a problem but
it's all Peter multi-sig setup because
say there are three of us or more of us
in a company and we just want to accept
bitcoins to a multi-sig lock-in script
will obviously have to construct this
lock-in script and give to someone else
and they'll have to construct a
transaction and put the entire script we
have given them into the locking code
for the bitcoins they are sending us
like so so they construct this entire
track transaction and they all have to
put the locking code that we want onto
this batch of bitcoins problem with this
check multi-sig is that they can get
these particular locking scripts can get
become quite big so this two or three
multi-sig locking script is a hundred
and five bytes but with every public key
that we add in to the pater multi-sig it
gets bigger and bigger and bigger
because every public key takes up 33
bytes of space inside transaction data
so if we were to give this you know a
very big locking script a very big paid
to multi-sig locking script to someone
to lock up our bitcoins they're probably
not gonna be very happy because this is
going to take up a lot of data inside
their transaction and they're gonna have
to pay for that data in transaction fees
so you know especially when you consider
that pay to public is 35 bytes paid to
public key hash 25 bytes and typically
the smallest peter multi-sig locking
script is gonna be 105 bytes it's not
too exciting for this person to want to
send bitcoins to anything other than
Peter pop key or pay to pokey hash
scripts so what can we do to sort of
avoid this problem of this person having
to pay for these large locking scripts
you know through creating transactions
that contain more trent data than they
would like so that's where peter script
ash comes in
it's basically there to make these more
complex scripts shorter and easier for
someone else to creat transactions with
so this is called peter script hash and
i'll explain how this works now so let's
say we want to receive bitcoins to a
peter multi-sig locking script what
we'll do instead of given them is in
this entire locking script your first of
all just hash it together
the unique hash of this particular
script and this is called the script
hash so what we can do then you can just
give this script hash to someone else
and then they can put this into the
locking script wrap it with a sick of a
set of opcodes and so there we have he
paid to script hash lock so it's
obviously a lot smaller so instead of
giving this person the entire original
locking script we just give them a hash
of it then which shrinks it shrinks it
down a lot they just have to apply to
opcodes around it and then we have a
page of script hash locking script and
this is much shorter so whereas the
original 105 bytes a page of script hash
is similar to a peter pub key hash about
23 bytes which makes them happy because
they don't have to construct these huge
transactions and pay for the fees from
these large locking scripts so that
works but then how do we unlock or
redeem this batch of bitcoins for this
painter script hash code on it lock and
script on it well what we do if it's a
peter multi-sig
same as before you just need to provide
two signatures but then in addition to
that we also have to provide the
original locking script though this hash
of the locking script was created from
but instead of putting the individual op
codes we just squeeze it all together
into a single piece of data or serialize
it to a single piece of data so all the
op codes are in there but instead of
them peered individual op codes it's
just a bunch of data right so let's run
this locking code and a knockin code
right so once again you put the locking
code at the start but the thing is with
a pager script hash and even though it
gets executed in roughly the same way
this particular format of locking code
is like it's a special form and it will
be executed slightly differently and
I'll show you how that works now so it
starts off as normal using the stack we
put the locking code at the start and we
all just push the signatures onto the
stack then we run into this see realized
lock in script also call the redeem
script and because it's just data just
shove together that just goes on top of
the stack as well and that is the
unlocking code part done because it's a
pager script hash this is where the
difference comes in it will make a copy
of the stack after the unlocking code or
a knockin script has been run so it
takes a copy of it now it will run the
original locking script with the stack
we've got from the unlocking script so
first of all it there's a hash 160 of
the top element on the stack so it will
hash this piece of data the
see realized lock-in script the original
one and they were hash it put it back on
top then the hash from the locking
script again put on top of the stack as
well and then they're equal opcode will
pop two elements off check that they
equal and if they are it'll put a one on
top of the stack and so this stack no
this script part the unlocking script
and the locking script has been
completely run and we are left with a 1
on top of the stack so this first part
checks that the locking script the
serialized locking script we've provided
matches the one that was originally
hashed and put into the locking script
so that part is done
then after it's been run because it's a
descriptive it brings the copy back and
uses that as the stack so the first part
checks that the the hash match is the
Redeem script that we provided and in
the second part of the page a script
hash it will pop the top element off
which is the regime script it will
deserialize it and then run the stack
again so like before in PT multi-sig
this is a number two gets pushed on top
then all the public keys then the three
then we went into chat multi C again
you'll do the exact same as last time
pop all the ailments off check the
signatures against public keys make sure
it's got enough and if that's correct
it'll push someone back onto the stack
and that is that done do you follow that
okay okay so this page of script hash
it's the only one that gets run a little
differently to these typical scripts and
it's only and it was added into Bitcoin
later on as a way to be able to create
simple complex scripts basically then
have other that have other people only
have to put a simple format of locking
script on top of bitcoins to make it
easier for them these peter script
hashes also have their own address
similar to the peter pub key hash so the
way you get a way you form an address
for a
pay to script hash locking script is you
will hash the script that you the
locking script they or basically how you
want this matchup it going to be locked
up like before great a hash remit and
then from this hash you will encode it
into a pretty format of an address and
you can go back and forth between these
two and whereas in a pay to pop key hash
you have the hash they create well in
this page script - you couldn't address
and the hash is inside there and you put
a three at the start so when you give
this three to someone else they'll be
able to decode it get the hash and then
form this particular format of locking
script so a one address I need any
address begins with the one corresponds
to this particular type of lock in
script and any address you find the
start with a three correspond to this
kind of locking script so it's typically
going to be you know a paid to multi-sig
or more recently pay into a segregated
witness type transaction which I'm not
going to cover here but segregated
witness has used this format for locking
up their coins so that's page script
hash then that's the most complex part
of this whole presentation so if that
made sense then everything else gonna be
easy
um but this is just like a special form
that gets asked executed slightly
differently finally the last standard
script that gets used in Bitcoin it's
called a null data locking script and
that uses this up code called opie
return or just return and what this our
code does it invalidates the script so
no matter what you put in the unlocking
code whenever you run or a node runs
this
up code it's going to invalidate the
script which means that this batch of
bitcoins can never be spent so why would
you do that it seems quite pointless why
would you create a batch of bitcoins
that can never be spent well what
typically happens in Bitcoin is they
someone will create a transaction but
then they'll also create a output with
no bitcoins in it so like an like almost
like a dummy output and in the locking
script they'll put the return opcode in
there so it can't be spent but there's
no bitcoins in there so you know be
spent anyway and then after the return
up code they'll just put some data after
it for example you could take the text
will you marry me convert to text XML
hexadecimal and put it in the lock in
script after this return up code and
this is a standard format for a or
standard transaction format so basically
this format is just a way of adding some
arbitrary data to a Bitcoin transaction
so when you hear people inserting data
into the blockchain this is the easiest
way for a typical person creating a
transaction to add data to the
blockchain you just create an empty
output and on the locking script use the
return opcode and put any teacher in
after it that you want
that make sense okay so that is the top
five or five main standard scripts using
bitcoins if you yeah is the use of the
return keyword kind of okay with the
community or the they are not very happy
sound very interesting right yeah I
think it is a bit controversial because
it kind should just be like a simple
transaction system but this noble turn
I'm not sure why yeah it was sort of
allowed or why it's allowed in a way I
don't understand because bitcoin is
quite strict really with you know it
wants to be a small database and this
just allows people to so I'm not sure a
bit but for the time being for now this
is a allowed standard script that you
can use to insert arbitrary data into
the blog chain through transactions
anyway so coming back to your question
earlier these are the standard scripts
that you're most commonly see on the
blockchain these top four obviously just
pay public keys this fifth one just like
an extra additional one
but inside the script pro mini
programming language you have a wide
variety of different operators so far
I've just covered these ones standard
scripts but you might have noticed that
we have these little numbers up codes
just just numbers then we also have some
other operators like mathematical winds
like addition and subtraction
conditional operators if and else and
then or sorry more hashing operators you
know like sha-256 and ymd 160 so you
know this script programming language
has a quite a few different opera op
codes that we can use to create
different types of scripts so for
example you could create a put a lock on
top of a batch of bitcoins there's just
a mathematical puzzle so you could use
add 8 and then equal so when when
someone comes to want to unlock this
script if they want to unlock it and
spend it all they need to do is provide
two numbers that when you add them then
so basically two numbers get pushed onto
the stack add will take those two add
them push them back onto the stack eight
goes on top of the stack and if those
two items on top of the stack are equal
then the bitcoins can be spent so for
example to unlock this batch of bitcoins
in the unlocking script you just need to
provide two numbers that add up to eight
like so similarly you could create a
hash puzzle so you could use a char 256
up code put some data in there after it
and then the equal up code so if you
want to unlock this batch of bitcoins
all you need to do is provide some data
that's hashes to this piece of data in
the locking code so this kind of locking
script you can find these on the
blockchain I haven't got any links off
the top of my head but you know you can
create scripts like these and they can
be mined onto the Bachchan however
in Bitcoin you can't create a
non-standard script but if you're trying
to insert it into a Bitcoin core node so
the Bitcoin coin program implementation
it actually keeps a list of standard
scripts so if you create one that is
non-standard they actually rejected
which is a bit of shame the reason for
that is as far as I'm aware it's because
there's a wide variety of these up codes
and operators and not all combinations
of them have been thoroughly tested so
it could be that someone could create a
combination of up codes that when they
insert the transaction into a node the
node might end up taking a while to
process it or validate it so all of the
standard scripts are known to be run
quickly and you know can be validated
quickly so to protect against anyone
trying to attack the network by creating
you know thousands of slow or expensive
to verify scripts and insert and enter
them into a node a Bitcoin or Bitcoin
core node will actually just reject
anything that's non-standard which i
think is a bit aim because you know
script it's a simple language but it
does have a variety of operators to use
and create scripts with but Bitcoin core
limits the number all the types of
scripts you can put on batches of
bitcoins however none that doesn't mean
that nonce on standard scripts are
actually invalid even though a Bitcoin
core node will reject them or not accept
them into their memory pools if a
non-standard script were to be mined
onto the blockchain then those blocks
would be valid so as long as the actual
script itself is valid you know contains
all the standard operators and data if
it gets mind into a block every noodle
accept it but they won't accept it if a
non-standard script
tries to enter their mempool
and the reason for that is the memory
pool can receive a large quantity of
transactions in a small period of time
so you know you could create a slow to
verify transaction and try and insert
thousands into the network which could
bring the network down because everyone
slowly trying to verify all these
non-standard transactions
however a block can only hold the
limited number of transactions so if
someone did insert you know stow to
verify transactions into a block because
blocks only get added every 10 minutes
they'll probably be validated it be
easier to validate them or be an ass of
a problem whereas having thousands of
non-standard scripts hit in the memory
pool could be a big risk but like I said
non-standard scripts are valid but
unfortunately it's hard to get their
mind onto the blockchain so I'm not sure
how you'll end up getting it mind if the
nodes don't accept it because even a
minor is like yeah right so yeah don't
make that make sense so options you have
which aren't many options is one to send
your non-standard transaction to a minor
who will accept them and will add it to
the proxy for you which I don't know of
any miners that you can send a
non-standard transaction to or secondly
which is an option but not necessarily
easy is just to mine it onto the pocket
in yourself so unless effort however
unless you've got a lot of processing
power that's gonna be a bit tricky so
you know practically you know you are
right you're probably not going to be
able to get a non-standard transactions
into the blockchain which is a very
shame however like I said it's only the
Bitcoin core implementation that keeps a
list i don't well it might be other ones
but you could create your Bitcoin node
written in your own programming language
with your own rules and you could accept
non-standard scripts but if there's no
one else you know on the network when in
your same software every time you try
and be lame
Bitcoin core knows they're just gonna
reject them so yeah for all intents and
purposes
unfortunately non-standard scripts are
not really going to be used and mind
onto the blockchain in Bitcoin at the
moment which i think is a bit of a shame
finally ok so that's basically
everything you need to know about script
and how it works if you understand all
these op codes and data and the stack
that's just how script works it's just a
mini programming language that executes
on a stack and if there's a one left on
top of the stack at the end the script
is valid and the bitcoins can be spent
so you know it was always like this or
more recently they actually stopped
allowing it because they probably wanted
to reduce the size of the block yeah I
think I think the standard you know
having this set of standard scripts was
in Bitcoin from the start but from what
I understand I know the restriction of
non-standard yeah I think ultimately it
was planned for it to be lifted so but
it hasn't happened so yeah so finally
where do you find you know I've done
I've just used simple you know locking
script and locking script you know
little diagrams to symbolize it where'd
you find this actual a knocking code
inside transaction data well like I said
when you make a Bitcoin transaction you
say this is transaction data you the
first part of transaction data just
selects an input so that's selecting
this input here and the second part
creates the output and so inside this
output code of transaction data contains
the script pub key which is the lock in
script so this part here this first part
is the amount of bitcoins and the second
part
I think I've highlighted I finally that
I did this a bit wrong but don't worry
this second part here is the script pub
key so move that there that is the
locking script as found inside
transaction data so where is the
unlocking script for this particular
locking script well that will appear in
a second transaction that tries to spend
this batch of bitcoins or this output so
in this second transaction you have an
input which all that does really is
reference an output from a previous
transaction so that's referencing this
year and the second transaction will
also create new outputs from it but what
we're interested in here in the second
transaction is the unlocking code so
when it references this previous output
inside the input sits the unlocking code
so this here is the unlocking code and
this is also referred to sometimes as a
script sig because it's a script and it
typically contains the signature for the
public key so there we have the
unlocking code so this is obviously or
in hexadecimal how do we get the opcodes
out of this well just need to decode it
if you weren't if we run through every
single byte inside the lock in script
and the unlocking script each byte will
correspond to a particular up code so
the byte in hexadecimal 76 is equal to
the tip or duplicate up code so there we
are a nine
that is hash 160 14 14 isn't actually
that doesn't have a corresponding opcode
but if anything is below for B in
hexadecimal what that means is that this
number indicates that this many bytes is
the piece of data to be pushed onto the
stack
so 14 is below for beef that says push
this many bytes onto the stack or this
is just the data and not an opcode so 14
in decimal is 20 bytes so there we have
this next 20 bytes it's just a piece of
data then carrying on we have 8 8 that's
equal verify and AC which is check sick
so then we ha
we've just decoded the docking script
it's just a bunch of bytes correspondent
opcodes
and if a byte is below a certain number
then that means the next X number of
bytes is a bunch of data so there we are
that's locking script decoded then we
come to the unlocking script and if you
remember all the unlocking script is is
free this particular kind of lock is
just a signature and a public key so 4 7
that's lesson for B so that's saying
this number of bytes is just in data and
that is the signature and then for when
this number of bytes and that is just a
more data again which is going to be the
public key so there we ha just decoded
the locking and unlocking script so make
sense ok so yeah the locking scripts can
be found
locking script is inside the output of
one transaction and then the Enochian
script is found in the input of a new
transaction that tries to spend the
image output
so there we are summarize now everything
that we've done in this video in a
Bitcoin transaction you just take a
batch of bitcoins akut create a new
batch from it and what do you want to
send it someone else they'll have a
public key they'll give you you know
probably an address and then your
construct the locking script for them
and lock up bitcoins until they either
the public key or the hash of their
public key so this one here this is this
particular format it's called pay to pop
key hash this is the locking script so
when you want to come to or this person
wants to come to spend these bitcoins
they will need to provide an unlocking
script like so and then this script will
get run so the unlocking script gets
provided second in the second
transaction but when we come to run the
full script together we put this at the
start so this gets added to the stack
first and then we run the script using
the opcodes and data and if a one is
left on the stack after you've run the
entire script then this batch of
bitcoins or the script is valid and this
batch bitcoins can be successfully
unlocked and spent and that is how the
mechanism for locking up bitcoins works
it works using this mini programming
language poor script that contains data
and up codes and it all works on top of
a stack this script has lots of
different approach
like so however we are the Bitcoin core
implementation kony restricts you to
these five main formats for locking up
bitcoins
and these are the four words you've got
Peter pepper key hash which is the most
commonly one used got Peter purp key
which is a simplified version of Peter
pop key hash but it's not really used
these days this page cache is the most
common one there we have Peter multi-sig
and then paint a script hash which is
just the easier way to pass around a
painting multi-sig lock in script like
so there we have script and how batches
of bitcoins are locked and unlocked in
Bitcoin any questions about that
presentation or any part of it
okay it's less tender than presentation
if that made sense then you understand
that script works I don't think it's
terribly difficult there only a few you
know things to note about the paid to
script hash part but the actual
execution of stuff is quite simple just
a simple programming language so yeah
involving and the other ones are pretty
yeah this page script hash he was sort
of added on to Bitcoin later on so it
wasn't part of the original
implementation so that's why it feels a
bit hacky I suppose but you know we were
sort of added on so it has these extra
rules of validation I made a little I
wrote some little bit of code to that
will basically decode or encode a script
and run it for you so if you wanted to
play with it it's very simple I wouldn't
use it properly in production it's more
just for us all of you know to learn
from it just to see how simple the
script is so for example
once cryptic odor it'll take a lock in
script so here's a typical Bitcoin
transaction obviously locking script and
unlocking scripted even provided for it
so it's been spent but say you wanted to
decode some script you can put the
locking script in there it's identified
that as a to pop key hash because it has
a special format so it's off to you
decoded it there and then when you want
to unlock something you need to provide
the locking script so there we are
this is just two pieces of data there's
no up codes in it so I want to run this
script and this little program will just
run it for you just to simulate it so
this is the entire script if I can pull
this across anyway so it's basically
just one big array of all the individual
pieces of the script so let's say this
is the stack here it pushes the data on
to the stack then this is the remainder
of the script so we got dope duplicate
here I'll duplicate the top element hash
160 and they'll hash table moment then
we've got the public key hash I guess
pressed on top equal verify that I'll
take the top two elements and if they're
equal we'll push anything back onto the
stack so after we've executed this these
two elements should disappear because
they are equal and then hope you check
sig so this will check this public key
against this signature and there we are
and so we'll push true on to the stack
true isn't actually using Bitcoin it
should be one but same thing so there we
are that's a valid script so I'll add a
link to this into the description if you
want to play with this code it's just
there so you can sort of see how the
code runs
alternatively if you go on Bitcoin dye
t4 just Wiki going to the script page it
covers all the different up codes that
you can use so I was you can see there's
quite a few I only really scratched the
surface of all the ones you can use but
like I said unfortunately we are
restricted really to only be able to use
the standard scripts even though script
does contain all these various different
codes lastly I found this little IDE
which allows you to enter a script and
it will visualize the running of the
script on the stack for you I think it
covers every single opcode so you know
you could add you know much more complex
script in here and then try and run it
and it will run it for you so I didn't
make this someone else did but it might
be a very good way to visualize how the
stack works and actually inserts your
own scripts and watch them run and it's
adhere I provide another link in the
description and then lastly if you want
to browse scripts on my blog in Explorer
go to any transaction as you can see
this is a transaction has inputs and
outputs click on the unlocking part or
the locking part and it will show you
the unlocking code also at the locking
code that was placed on top of the
transaction and this was the subsequent
and locking code so when you run this
all together you'll put this onto a
stack you should be able to visualize
you know it all working or hopefully
doesn't actually visualize anything for
you but you know all the opcodes and
data is there if you to look at and
maybe get a feel for